That's why I went and got a new computer. Good morning. Today
is the 10th of אייר. Iyar. I don't know the... what are
we on, the 25th of the עומר, Omer, which means it's May
20-something, no, 18th. 18th. Okay. I'm Dan Margolis, filling in for Rabbi
Linzer while he's away. And today's דף daf is ס"ח, Samech-Chet, but
we're going to be starting at ס"ז עמוד ב Samech-Zayin Amud Bet
right towards the end of the narrow lines on ס"ז עמוד ב,
Samech-Zayin Amud Bet, the last three narrow lines. נתגיירו הלך אחר הפגום
שבשניהם. Nitgaiyru Halach Achar Hapgum Shebishneihem.
So the משנה Mishnah was talking about basically four different kinds of
cases regarding ייחוס, yichus, under which sorts of cases and grouped, I
think using rather interesting descriptions, about how different cases of marriage with
among people who are maybe not meant to marry each other, maybe
are allowed to marry each other, but how different ייחוס yichus is
transmitted and communicated throughout. And in a case where one or perhaps
both of, in this case, both of the parties getting married have
converted, particularly the concern here is converted from nations who have restrictions
on their marital prospects like Egyptians, Edomites, not Edomites, Ammonites and Moabites.
And so those three nations, מצרי, Mitzri, עמוני, Amoni, and מואבי, Moavi,
there are restrictions about how they can marry into the Jewish people
or whom they have to marry. So they would be allowed to
marry converts and ממזרים mamzerim and things like that, but there would
be a higher standard for them to not marry into the
fully Jewish or fully
acceptably higher level ייחוס yichus Jewish community. נתגיירו הלך אחר הפגום שבשניהם.
Nitgaiyru Halach Achar Hapgum Shebishneihem. So you have to follow the most
פגום pagum that follow from either of them. That's what the משנה
Mishnah sounds like. So the גמרא Gemara asks, במאי? Bemai? What are
we talking about? אילימא במצרי שנשא עמונית? Eleima beMitzri shenasa Amonit? Are
we talking about an Egyptian man
whose descendants for three generations would not, male descendants would not be
allowed to marry into the Jewish people? They would have to still
marry a convert and things like that. So if an Egyptian man
married an Ammonite woman, מאי פגום איכא? Mai pagum ika? עמוני ולא
עמונית. Amoni velo Amonit. There's no problem of the woman. That is
a female Ammonite. We know that דרשה drasha comes up already in
מסכת ידיים Masechet Yadayim and it's the discussion imposed by the מדרש
Midrash on much of ספר רות Sefer Rut is about how much
are Moabite and Ammonite women excluded. And the תורה שבעל פה Torah
Shebal Peh understanding at least is that they are not excluded from
marrying into the Jewish people at all. And that's why Rut was
able to marry Boaz and that's not any kind of a problem.
Yeah, I'm sorry, where are you?
The last narrow line of ס"ז עמוד ב. Samech-Zayin Amud Bet. Fine,
thanks. מצרי שנשא עמונית מאי פגום איכא עמוני ולא עמונית.
Mitzri
shenasa Amonit, mai pagum ika?
Amoni velo Amonit. So there's no problem for a female Ammonite to
marry into the Jewish people, and in this case, so you would
follow... her children should be fine.
There's no, there's no, there's no competing, competing problems of two different
kinds of פגום, pagum, rather because the male, the husband is Egyptian,
so that's a problem, but for his wife who is an Ammonite
convert, there
would be
no problem.
אלא בעמוני שנשא מצרית. Ella beAmoni shenasa Mitzrit. So a male Ammonite
convert who married a female Egyptian convert. So in that case, the
husband is עמוני, Amoni, so he has a certain level of restriction,
which is a high level restriction, and מצרית Mitzrit is unisex, that
is applies to or non-gendered
kind of restriction, and therefore the מצרית, Mitzrit, her descendants would follow
the rules of מצרי, Mitzri, which would be for three generations. So
therefore, ואי זכר הוי האי שדיא בתריה דידיה. Veim zachar havei, hai
shadia batrei dideih.
So if they have a male child, then it should follow the
ייחוס yichus of the father. ואי נקבה הוי שדיא בתרה דידה. Veim
nekeiva havei, shadia batrah didah.
And if it is a female child, then their daughter would follow
the ייחוס yichus of the mother. That is, if a daughter is
born, the daughter would be treated like an Egyptian of second generation,
and if a son would be born, it would be treated like
an עמוני, Amoni, which lasts forever.
So how is this הלך אחר הפגום שבשניהם? Halach Achar Hapgum Shebishneihem?
Because the children, which children follow which parent? So it's not the
way I initially would have read the משנה, Mishnah, that you would
just sort of take the worst of the two. It actually is
this kind of... you split the children based on their genders, how
it seems like.
So I have another question, which I'm trying to understand, like so
2000 years later, so someone now from let's say they're...
okay, so this is a very important principle.
Assuming that they're Egyptian, right? Let's pretend that we know that they're
Egyptian. But we don't. No, I'm just saying, but I'm trying to
understand first
conceptually.
So then... So the Torah gives you mitzvot that at least understanding,
you know, traditional understanding is that the mitzvot are meant to last
for all generations. And therefore the prohibition for a מצרי Mitzri to
marry into the Jewish people for three generations would last any מצרי
Mitzri and any time is still going to have a three-generation barrier
to entry, rather than saying it's just the three generations after יציאת
מצרים. Yetziat Mitzrayim. It's certainly an interesting discussion to have about what
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is in terms of, it
might be a very good פשט, pshat, but in terms of הלכה
halacha it's always been understood, at least as far as I know,
I haven't done extensive research about it, but it's been understood that
way. That it is whenever someone would convert, there's still that three-generation
barrier. And you can imagine three generations is a long time to
have restrictions on someone's ייחוס. yichus. 75 years
let's say, something like that. So that means a person converts, their
children are born Jewish but they're second generation מצרי. Mitzri. Second generation
מצרי Mitzri marries people who he or she is allowed to marry.
Their children are third generation מצרי, Mitzri, and after that their children
would be fine. So that's a big thing to keep track of.
Okay, כל שאין לה עליו קידושין. kol she-ein la alav kidushin. Now
we're going to get into a major discussion across ש"ס Shas and
really here is one of the central places, which is the question
of what causes ממזרות mamzerus and what, what is the link between
prohibition of being married or getting married and a ממזר. mamzer. That
is, a ממזר mamzer is someone usually translated as a bastard, but
obviously the rules of ממזר mamzer are much more complex and sophisticated
than the general colloquialism. And also it's important to note that unlike
many people think, a child born out of wedlock between two people
who are allowed to marry each other is no ממזר. mamzer. That's
not what ממזר mamzer is about. ממזר mamzer fundamentally is linked, at
least according to most of the תנאים, Tanna'im, to the prohibition upon
getting married. Now we're going to see there's a three-way, four-way מחלוקת
machlokes between the תנאים. Tanna'im. רבי שמעון התימני Rabbi Shimon HaTimni says
that the reason, what causes ממזרות mamzerus is חייבי כריתות. chayvei kraitot.
That is, whichever עריות, arayot, whichever forbidden relationships, which the punishment is
כרת kareit or מיתת בית דין, mitat beit din, that is capital
crimes or כרת. kareit. Those, the קידושין kidushin does not take effect
and the children would be ממזרים. mamzerim. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has
a much more expansive notion. רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position we saw
in יבמות Yevamot and other places already. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thinks
that חייבי לאוין, chayvei lavin, that is any prohibited relationship with a
negative commandment. There are certain ones, very few, which are חייבי עשה
chayvei asei or איסור עשה, issur asei, but most forbidden marriages are
some kind of a prohibition. And therefore רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
there's no תפיסת קידושין, tfisat kidushin, that means the קידושין kidushin does
not work, and the children would be ממזרים. mamzerim. And רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua has an even more narrow opinion than רבי שמעון התימני.
Rabbi Shimon HaTimni. He says the only thing that creates ממזרות mamzerus
is מיתת בית דין. mitat beit din. That is those עריות arayot
which are actually capital crimes. And many of them are שריפה, sereifah,
some are סקילה, skilah, some are חנק, chenek, but things like that,
but not those which are punished with כרת. karet.
What about
in-vitro fertilizations? That doesn't actually have to have sex or is it
just a union, meaning like?
No, so that's exactly the point, that in order for the child
to be a ממזר mamzer certainly there has to be a sexual
relationship.
So if you just do in-vitro, there's no ממזר. mamzer.
It could be. That's a major debate that comes out about the
in-vitro fertilization debate or artificial insemination debate in the פוסקים. poskim. רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein famously was the permissive opinion about those
sort of advanced reproductive technologies, and as far as I know most
people nowadays agree with רב משה'ס Rav Moshe's argument. The סאטמר רב
Satmar Rav was very opposed to any sort of artificial insemination or
in-vitro fertilization. He felt that the doctor administering artificial insemination or something
like that would be considered to be the active male party in
the fertilization and therefore would be considered an adulterous act. רב משה
Rav Moshe used many מקורות mekorot I think to convincingly argue against
that, but that was a major debate back when those technologies were
first being
developed.
Okay, so מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? Did you read the
מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? You read those?
No, we're about to do that. כל שאין לה עליו קידושין. Kol
she-ein la alav kidushin. That is, anyone for whom there is no
קידושין kidushin for him. What did the משנה mishna say? This is
the third category. מי שאין לה עליו קידושין אבל יש לה על
אחרים קידושין הולד ממזר. Mi she-ein la alav kidushin aval yesh la
al acherim kidushin ha-velad mamzer.
That is a ממזר mamzer is a case where this man and
this woman cannot get married but this woman in general could marry
another man. That's what the משנה mishna suggested. So let's see here.
מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? How do we know that that's
what causes ממזרות? mamzerus? דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן
ומטי בה משום רבי ינאי ורבי אחא בריה דרבא ומטי בה משום
רבי יוסי הגלילי. De-amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan u-mati
bah mishum Rabbi Yannai ve-Rabbi Acha bereih de-Rabba u-mati bah mishum Rabbi
Yossi Ha-Gelili. So three different opinions about who said this, but this
is the דרשה. drasha. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says:
ויצאה מביתה והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר. Ve-yatz'ah mi-beitah ve-halchah ve-haytah le-ish acher.
Talking
about... About divorce, the woman leaves this man's house and she can
go off and marry another man, לאחרים ולא לקרובים. l'acherim v'lo likrovim.
She could marry other people, but not his relatives. And that is
there is not only a prohibition of marriage, which we already know
from many other places in the תורה, Torah, but also that the
קידושין kiddushin would not take effect. That is, when a woman divorces
her husband, she would be not allowed to marry his father, son,
brother, etc. And all of those קרובים, krovim, all of those relatives
that create the levels of עריות, arayot, and then that דרשה drasha
becomes a basis for excluding any קידושין kiddushin taking effect between עריות
arayot of that level.
אחר. Acher. Exactly. Okay.
We can do the whole calculus of which דרשות drashot work for
whom and how and we're going to see here there's going to
be some question about dealing with some hanging דרשות drashot about רבי
עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position. So we're going to see. So מתקיף לה
רבי אבא. Matkif lah Rabbi Abba. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba asks, ואימא
לאחר ולא לבן? V'eima l'acher v'lo l'ven? So why not just very
limited? She could marry someone else just not this man's son, but
not to קרובים krovim in general, relatives in general. בן בהדיא כתיב
ביה, Ben b'hedya ketiv beih, because a son is mentioned explicitly: לא
יקח איש את אשת אביו. Lo yikach ish et eshet aviv. A
man is not allowed to marry the wife of his father. That
is, a woman cannot marry the son of her ex-husband. However, so
in that פסוק pasuk says לא יקח. lo yikach. Now לא יקח
lo yikach means he cannot marry or is not permitted to marry,
but also means that the קידושין kiddushin would not take effect. So
אחר למה לי? Acher lamah li? So then why do I have
this פסוק pasuk that talks about לאיש אחר? l'ish acher? So שמע
מינה לאחרים ולא לקרובים. Shma mina l'acherim v'lo likrovim.
So רבי אבא'ס Rabbi Abba's objection is refuted. ואימא אידי ואידי לבן.
V'eima idi v'idi l'ven. So maybe they're both referring to marrying the
ex-husband's son and therefore that would, there'd be no extension to the
lack of קידושין kiddushin for any of the other עריות. arayot. הא
לכתחילה והא בדיעבד? Ha l'chatchila v'ha b'diavad? And maybe one says לכתחילה
l'chatchila you're not allowed to get married, but the second פסוק pasuk
is necessary to teach us בדיעבד b'diavad that even if you tried
to get married, it does not work. לכתחילה מאחות אשה נפקא. L'chatchila
m'achot isha nafka. No, the fact that it's prohibited we can learn
from אחות אשה. achot isha. אחות אשה, Achot isha, the your sister's
wife, a
sister's wife, sorry.
So a man to marry his wife's sister is one of the
עריות. arayot. In the beginning of יבמות Yevamot if you remember and
here also is going to form the basis, some kind of a
בניין אב binyan av to extend to all of the עריות, arayot,
and that is that number one, צרת ערווה tzarat ervah is classically
learned from אחות אשה achot isha and also here the עריות arayot
the אי תפיסת קידושין ee-tfisat kiddushin by עריות, arayot, that is that
the קידושין kiddushin does not take effect with any of the עריות.
arayot. So here אחות אשה, achot isha, that is your wife's sister,
becomes the paradigm for the fact that you could not get married.
Not just that it would be prohibited to get married but the
marriage would not take place. So נפקא? nafka? ומה אחות אשה בכרת,
u-mah achot isha b'karet, just like אחות אשה achot isha the punishment
is כרת, karet, לא תקדש, lo tikadesh, and you cannot get married,
חייבי מיתות בית דין לא כל שכן? chayavei mitot beit din lo
kol sheken? We try to learn a קל וחומר kal vachomer from
כרת karet to חייבי מיתה, chayavei mita, that is capital crimes are
even more severe than כרת karet and therefore just like it is
impossible to marry your wife's sister, so too any of the מיתות
בית דין, mitot beit din, that is עריות arayot that the punishment
is a capital offense,
you would not be able to get married. Okay, לא כל שכן,
lo kol sheken, you can make that קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. But it's forbidden to marry אחות אשה achot isha after
גירושין. geirushin. Correct. What about after the death?
After the death, that's mentioned explicitly in the תורה Torah and it's
the only exception,
the
only ערווה ervah whose status changes after the death of another
person. So because we know, we have דרשות, drashot, that's the rule.
But so אחות אשה achot isha sister-in-law, and now it's very interesting,
at the beginning of יבמות Yevamot the whole tension is between two
different sisters-in-law or two different brothers-in-law. That is, your wife's sister becomes
the paradigm for the prohibition to do יבום, yibum, the exemption from
יבום, yibum, but your brother's wife is where the מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum is
located. Exactly that tension between two different kinds of in-law relationships and
obviously it tells us a lot about what the תורה Torah sees
as the basis of the family unit and how different clans are
interacting with each other. There's a lot to say about that if
we were learning יבמות. Yevamot. Okay.
It's not a very good קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It's not a
very good קל וחומר kal vachomer
in that why?
Well, first of all, you just, one could posit that the reason
the תורה Torah requires a death sentence of a worse punishment is
because the קידושין kiddushin is תופס. tofes.
Okay, so you could make some kind of an argument there that
there's just different levels. Meaning what's more חמור? chamur? Is it more
חמור chamur that the קידושין kiddushin should work or is it more
חמור chamur that the קידושין kiddushin should not work? We don't really
have any intuition about that. Okay. ואימא אידי ואידי באחות אשה? V'eima
idi v'idi b'achot isha? הא לכתחילה והא בדיעבד? Ha l'chatchila v'ha b'diavad?
So maybe we should say no, both of them are referring to
אחות אשה achot isha and therefore we can't make this קל וחומר
kal vachomer because אחות אשה achot isha is isolated with its own
rule that the קידושין kiddushin does not work for אחות אשה, achot
isha, but it can't be extended to everything. אי הכי נמי אשכחן
אחות אשה שאר עריות מנלן? I hachi nami ashkhachan achot isha she'ar
arayot minalan? ומנא לן ילפינן מאחות אשה מה אחות אשה. Umina lan
yalfinan me'achot isha mah achot isha. So no, so everything else, all
the other עריות arayot we have to learn from אחות אשה. Achot
Isha. מה אחות אשה מיוחדת שהיא ערוה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ושגגתה
חטאת לא תפסי בה קידושין. Mah achot isha miyuchedet shehi ervah vechayavin
al zedonah karet veshigegatah chatat lo tafsi bah kiddushin. Just like אחות
אשה Achot Isha is מיוחדת, miyuchedet, she is unique ערוה ervah status
in that the קידושין Kiddushin does not work, and the punishment is
כרת, karet, and if you did it בשוגג b'shogeg you bring a
קרבן חטאת korban chatat and the קידושין Kiddushin does not take effect.
אף כל שהיא ערוה וחייבין על זדונה כרת ושגגתה חטאת לא תפסי
בה קידושין. Af kol shehi ervah vechayavin al zedonah karet veshigegatah chatat
lo tafsi bah kiddushin. So we should make a בנין אב binyan
av from אחות אשה Achot Isha to say so too any ערוה
ervah where the punishment is כרת karet and therefore you should say
that the קידושין Kiddushin would not take hold either. בשלמא כולהו אתיין.
Bishlama kulhu atyan.
So maybe we should say all of them that that's fine, that
works, okay. אלא אשת איש ואשת אח איכא למפרך. Ela eshet ish
ve'eshet ach ika lemefrach. We have two exceptions.
Wait, I'm just getting lost in the trees here. What are we
trying to do?
So we're trying to establish the fact that those עריות arayot for
whom the punishment is כרת karet or perhaps מיתת בית דין mitat
beit din as well, those cases if you tried to get married,
the קידושין Kiddushin would not take effect. Okay? So
so far the argument has been that's learned from a בנין אב
binyan av from אחות אשה. Achot Isha. That is אחות אשה, Achot
Isha, your wife's sister, if you would try to marry your wife's
sister, in that case the קידושין Kiddushin would not take effect because
the punishment of marrying your wife's sister is כרת. karet. And כרת
karet
and it's explicit it seems that the קידושין Kiddushin would not take
effect. Therefore, we could extend that to every other ערוה ervah whose
punishment is כרת. karet.
The גמרא Gemara assumes that כרת karet is a חמור chamur more
punishment than מיתה? mita?
No, it's less חמור, chamur, right?
Whatever כרת karet is, and it's I think a five-way מחלוקת machloket
in the ראשונים Rishonim what כרת karet is,
but dying prematurely, dying without children, or some kind of spiritual punishment
to your נשמה neshama after you die. There's a lot, a lot
written. The רמב"ם Rambam in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim discusses extensively. Okay,
so even if we're able to learn from אחות אשה Achot Isha
there's still going to be two exceptions: אשת איש eshet ish and
אשת אח. eshet ach. אשת איש, eshet ish, a married woman in
general, and אשת אח, eshet ach, exactly the opposite kind of sister-in-law,
that is your brother's wife. Now your brother's wife could be the
same person as your wife's sister because that's the classic case of
צרת ערוה, tzarat ervah, that is two brothers each of them married
to two sisters. So then the two wives are sisters and the
two husbands are brothers and that would be a problem. So we're
going to see. מה לאחות אשה שכן אין לה היתר במקום מצוה.
Mah l'achot isha sheken ein lah heter b'makom mitzvah. So אחות אשה
Achot Isha is never permissible. There's no exemption for אחות אשה. Achot
Isha. That's something that beats יבום. yibum. תאמר באשת אח שיש לה
היתר במקום מצוה. Tomar b'eshet ach she'yesh lah heter b'makom mitzvah. So
אשת אח eshet ach obviously we know that's when the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibum applies and therefore there's an exemption. So that level
of ערוה ervah is different or is certainly less severe than any
of the other עריות arayot because there's a special requirement to marry
and to procreate with one's
brother's wife after his death. That's the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum.
In a sense that would apply to none of the other עריות,
arayot, is a special exemption. Okay, so there's no room for that.
ואשת איש נמי איכא למפרך. Ve'eshet ish nami ika lemefrach. We can
also bring a challenge, we can undermine this בנין אב binyan av
from אשת איש. eshet ish. אשת איש, eshet ish, just any married
woman. מה להנך שכן אין היתר בחיי אוסרן? Mah l'hanach sheken ein
heter b'chayei osran? תאמר באשת איש שיש לה היתר בחיי אוסרן. Tomar
b'eshet ish sheyesh lah heter b'chayei osran. So any of the other
עריות arayot except for אחות אשה Achot Isha interestingly enough, any of
the other עריות arayot there's no היתר heter during the lifetime of
the one who created the איסור. issur. That is and even afterwards.
Meaning אחות אשה Achot Isha applies while the wife is still alive.
All of the other עריות arayot apply whether or not חיי אוסרן
chayei osran at all. They apply forever. And אשת איש, eshet ish,
there's a way to remove the איסור issur of אשת איש eshet
ish during the lifetime of the one who created that איסור, issur,
that is the husband and wife get divorced. So that's a way
of reducing the severity of the ערוה ervah of אשת איש. eshet
ish. אשת איש eshet ish is a lower level איסור issur in
that sense that logically because there's a way to get out of
it, it makes it a less severe level of ערוה ervah and
you could not apply this בנין אב binyan av to that to
say if you tried to marry a married woman that the קידושין
Kiddushin would not work. Interestingly enough the אחרונים achronim try to pick
up on this extensively. It sounds like here the discussion about why
marrying a married woman does not work is about ערוה. ervah. It
doesn't seem like it has anything to do with the fact that
a woman can't be married to two men at once or something
to do with the קנין kinyan side of the קידוש, kiddush, it
really seems like it has to do just with the relational aspect,
which is very interesting. It seems to go against a lot of
what we've read before. אלא אמר רבי יונה. Ela amar Rabbi Yona.
So what does רבי יונה Rabbi Yona say? A different approach. ואי
תימא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Ve'i teima Rav Huna breih deRav
Yehoshua, or it was רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Rav Huna breih
deRav Yehoshua. אמר קרא כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו. Amar
kra kol asher ya'aseh mikol hato'evot ha'eleh venichretu. So the sum up
פסוק pasuk at the end of the פרשה parsha of עריות arayot
says whoever does any of these תועבות to'evot will be will receive
כרת. karet. הוקשו כל העריות כולהן לאחות אשה. Hukshu kol ha'arayot kulehan
l'achot isha. And therefore all of the עריות arayot are summed up
together in one lump category connected to אחות אשה. Achot Isha. מה
אחות אשה לא תפסי בה קידושין. Mah achot isha lo tafsi bah
kiddushin. just like אחות אשה, achot isha, you, the קידושין kiddushin does
not take effect, אף כל העריות כולם לא תפסי בה קידושין. af
kol ha'arayot kulam lo tafsi bah kiddushin. Therefore
any of the other עריות, arayot, the קידושין kiddushin would not take
effect either.
Okay, תוספות Tosafot just to note that the תוספות מנהני מילי, Tosafot
m'hanei milei, תוספות Tosafot there discusses how much are the lack of
קידושין kiddushin and the status of ממזרות mamzerut connected. That is, are
there cases where they don't necessarily impact each other? And תוספות Tosafot
seems to take very strongly that actually one causes the other. Now
still the question remains which one causes the other one. There are
a lot of other מקורות mekorot especially in יבמות Yevamot talking about
that extensively. So now a major challenge to this point. We just
said, okay so we have a different פסוק, pasuk, the sum-up פסוק
pasuk at the end of all of the פרשה parsha of עריות
arayot connects all the עריות arayot to אחות אשה. achot isha. So
what's the major exception that we have to ask about? אי הכי
אפילו נדה נמי. i hachi afilu niddah nami. So what about נדה?
niddah? נדה niddah is mentioned in the list of עריות, arayot, a
menstruant woman is on the list of ערווה, ervah, but we know,
and this is the גמרא Gemara is going to make explicit, that
the child born to a woman who is נדה niddah is obviously
not a ממזר. mamzer. And so therefore the understanding that נדה niddah
is listed among the עריות arayot but is actually qualitatively very different
from the other עריות. arayot. Important to note the תוספות הראש Tosafot
HaRosh on יבמות דף ב, Yevamot daf bet, there in the discussion
of a similar discussion about how much the different עריות arayot are
exemptions from the מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, so תוספות Tosafot on
the first דף daf of יבמות Yevamot talks about what about נדה?
niddah? Isn't נדה niddah one of the עריות arayot also? And so
therefore if one of the צרות tzarot of the man who passed
away was נדה niddah at the time he died, then that would
be an exemption based on צרת ערווה tzarat ervah that all of
the women would be exempt from doing יבום. yibbum.
Does he mean that seriously?
That's תוספות's Tosafot question. Now תוספות Tosafot has an answer and תוספות
הראש Tosafot HaRosh takes it one step further. תוספות הראש Tosafot HaRosh
says נדה niddah is not called an ערווה ervah really. Even though
it's on the list of עריות, arayot, fundamentally a different type of
ערווה, ervah, and that's similar to the תוספות Tosafot in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
that talks about why the laws of ייחוד yichud don't apply equally
between obviously married partners during נדה niddah period compared to any of
the other עריות. arayot. So there are a lot of differences between
נדה niddah and other עריות arayot and many of the אחרונים, achronim,
particularly בריסקערס, Briskers,
the בריסקער רב Brisker Rav in his book on the רמב"ם Rambam
in the back has a piece about why is נדה niddah different
than other עריות arayot and a few other אחרונים achronim pick up
on that as a really major distinction between נדה niddah and the
rest.
How can אחות אשה achot isha here be the main paradigm of
this דרשה? drasha? Again, if she dies then her sister becomes מותרת.
muteret. Yes. So how can, again, if you establish a בנין אב
binyan av you want an inviolable paradigm?
Right, they're not picking up on that detail I guess because that
detail is sort of more, it's built into אחות אשה achot isha
in a way that the other עריות arayot don't have any obvious
exemption or obvious way of getting out of them. That's the point.
Right, but it's just, oh you'll say that that's, meaning you could
always challenge the whole construct and say yeah, but אחות אשה achot
isha is less severe because of this. Yeah.
The תלמוד Talmud is not bothered by that.
The תלמוד Talmud is not bothered by that. It was mentioned a
little bit before about the question of אין לה היתר בחיי אוסרן
ein lah heter b'chayei osran and יש לה היתר בחיי אוסרן, yesh
lah heter b'chayei osran, but in this new דרשה drasha you could
ask the same question of רבי יונה Rabbi Yona as well. It's
a good question.
Does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan know that דרשה drasha two lines above?
I don't know. Okay. אי הכי אפילו נדה נמי.
i hachi
afilu niddah nami. So what about נדה? niddah? And רש"י Rashi here
just to clarify what case are we talking about, אם קידש פנויה
בימי נדותה, im kidesh pnuyah b'imei niddutah, what if you went and
married an unmarried woman during her period of נדה? niddah? לא הוי
קידושין מבאלי הנידתא להיות הולד ממזר. lo havei kiddushin m'ba'alei haniddutah lihyot
havlad mamzer. That's the הוה אמינא, hava amina, that you would not
be able to get married to a woman who is נדה niddah
and that the child would be a ממזר. mamzer. So under that
circumstance, now again, the separate question is one of what about if
you tried to do נישואין nisuin during when the woman is נדה?
niddah? That's called חופת נדה. chupat niddah. Most of the ראשונים rishonim
think it's not such a problem. The רמב"ם Rambam quotes the opinion
that actually the נישואין nisuin does not work when the woman is
נדה niddah and you have to, would have to redo the נישואין
nisuin or something like that. And in practical cases there end up
being ways that we avoid having to deal with that in any
serious way, but it can be a bit, it can be a
bit complicated in real life. But basically you end up trying to
make sure that the husband and wife aren't in ייחוד yichud together
until after
נדה. niddah.
Do they go to the ייחוד yichud room?
Right, they would avoid that in whatever way, either have someone else
come with them so it looks like they're going to the ייחוד
yichud room. It becomes a bit
complicated.
But how do they do נישואין? nisuin?
They do נישואין nisuin afterwards when they're living together at home afterwards.
But חופה chuppah needs ייחוד yichud also in other words?
Right, or the
חופה chuppah and then they have in mind קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah
then?
No, not קידושי ביאה, kiddushei biah, the קידושין kiddushin worked and then
the question is when does the נישואין nisuin take effect?
נישואי ביאה nisuei biah or whatever else.
I mean the נישואין nisuin will be, well that's when once they're
living together. But that becomes a bit more complicated. Anyway, so אמר
אביי amar Abaye הכל מודין בבא על הנדה ועל הסוטה שאין הולד
ממזר. hakol modin b'va al haniddah v'al hasotah she'ein havlad mamzer. So
according to אביי Abaye everyone, that is according to רבי שמעון התימני
Rabbi Shimon HaTimni and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who would think, well
not רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, according to רבי שמעון התימני Rabbi Shimon
HaTimni who... thinks any חייב כרת chayav kareit the child would be
a ממזר, mamzer, even he agrees that in case of נידה niddah
the child is not a ממזר. mamzer. That is נידה niddah is
an exception to the rule of the חייבי כריתות, chayevei kraitot, and
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who thinks that חייבי לאוין chayevei
lavin the child is a ממזר, mamzer, even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
thinks that סוטה sotah is an exemption from חייבי לאוין. chayevei lavin.
That is, not just סוטה, sotah, the whole process of סוטה, sotah,
but also סוטה, sotah, any woman who had an adulterous relationship, that's
an איסור לאו issur lav for her husband to be with her,
but a child born of that relationship afterward, that is a woman
had adultery with someone and then returned and had a child with
the husband, nonetheless, the child would not be a ממזר. mamzer.
Which is an important exemption as well. So those two cases, בבא
על הנידה ובבא על הסוטה שאין הולד ממזר. beva al haniddah uveva
al hasotah she'ein havlad mamzer. אמר חזקיה אמר קרא ותהי נדתה עליו.
Amar Chizkiyah amar kra utehi niddatah alav. So חזקיה Chizkiyah says it's
learned as a special exemption for נידה niddah because the פסוק pasuk
says ותהי נדתה עליו. utehi niddatah alav. This is talking about the
fact that a man who has sex with a woman while she
is in her state of נידה, niddah, he is called a בועל
נידה boel niddah and he acquires the impurity, the טומאה, tumah, for
seven days, just like she has for seven days. So that's explicit
in the תורה. Torah. ותהי נדתה עליו. Utehi niddatah alav. So we
make a דרשה drasha from the word ותהי, utehi, אפילו בשעת נדתה
תהא בה הויה. afilu bish'at niddatah tehei bah havayah. That is,
the word להיות lehiyot is connected in the תורה Torah many times
to the idea of marriage. Therefore, it is permissible or is possible
to get married to a woman while she's in נידה, niddah, even
though it's a חיובי כריתות. chiyuvei kareit. Okay, מכדי, mikdei, איכא לאוקשי
לנידה ואיכא לאוקשי לאחות אשה. ika le'ukshei leniddah ve'ika le'ukshei leachot isha.
So then how come all of the עריות arayot in general? You
could pick to connect them to נידה, niddah, which has a much
more permissive approach. That is, נידה niddah we know explicitly from the
תורה, Torah, נידה niddah you could marry, and אחות אשה achot isha
we know you cannot marry. It's physically impossible or legally impossible to
get married to אחות אשה. achot isha. So we could make this
היקש hekkesh of all of the עריות arayot could be connected to
one or the other. So why did you pick one over the
other? So מה חזית דמקישת להו לאחות אשה ואוקשי לנידה? mai chazi
demakshei lehu leachot isha ve'yakshei leniddah? So why can't we just make
a היקש hekkesh to נידה? niddah? כולהו בחומרא לחומרא מקשינן. kula bechumra
lechumra makshinan.
That when we have a היקש, hekkesh, היקש hekkesh we always choose
the most מחמיר machmir thing to connect them to. Now, that's an
interesting question methodologically, it's an interesting question. Is it true across all
the other היקישים hekkeshim throughout ש"ס? Shas? So I don't know for
sure, but it's certainly an interesting thing to flag as one of
these sort of כללים klallim about how the different דרשות drashot work,
to think about for other cases, that at least the גמרא Gemara
here suggests when you have a choice of two different things to
make a היקש hekkesh to, you make a היקש hekkesh to whatever
is the most מחמיר. machmir.
Is that based on ספק דאורייתא לחומרא?
safek deoraita lechumra? I think not. This sounds like a rule of
דרשה. drasha. דרשות drashot we understand generally to be וודאי, vadai, the
rabbinic law that the rabbis have made on solid footing. So here
it seems a bit strange that it's kind of an arbitrary rule
almost on how to determine the היקש. hekkesh. But it's something to
think about. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר אתיא בקל וחומר מיבמה.
Rav Acha bar Yaakov
amar: atya be-kal vachomer mi-yevama. No, we could learn it from קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. מה יבמה שהיא בלאו לא תפסי בה קידושין. ma
yevama shehi belav lo tafsi bah kiddushin. Just like a יבמה, yevama,
another exception. יבמה yevama is an איסור לאו. issur lav. That is,
it's only punishable with lashes. That is, a woman whose husband died
and she doesn't have any children and she has to do ייבום
yibbum with her brother-in-law, but suppose she would go and try to
marry someone else. So we know in this case, יבמה yevama is
only a לאו lav prohibition, the least severe kind of prohibition, but
לא תפסי בה קידושין.
lo tafsi
bah kiddushin.
A יבמה yevama can't get married. But let's note that's because at
least seemingly is based on the understanding that יש זיקה. yesh zika.
That is, the relationship between the יבם yavam and יבמה yevama already
starts automatically at the time that the brother died rather than
anytime later. That is, there is already the beginnings of something almost
like a קידושין. kiddushin.
It's like a, right, just like a proto-אשת איש. eshet ish.
Somehow like that. So יבמה לשוק yevama lashuk may be somewhat different
than other עריות arayot or not really ערווה, erva, it's איסור לאו.
issur lav. So לא תפסי בה קידושין. lo tafsi bah kiddushin. חייבי
מיתה וחייבי כריתות כל שכן. Chayevei mita ve-chayevei kraitot kol she-ken. So
couldn't we make this קל וחומר? kal vachomer? According to רב אחא
בר יעקב? Rav Acha bar Yaakov? אי הכי שאר חייבי לאוין נמי.
Ei hachi, shear chayevei lavin nami. So then we would have to
extend it to all other חייבי לאוין chayevei lavin as well. And
we don't want to have to פסקן pasken like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that every חייבי לאו chayevei lav you cannot get married to.
אמר רב פפא חייבי לאוין בהדיא כתיב בהו כי תהיין לאיש שתי
נשים. Amar Rav Pappa: chayevei lavin be-hedaya ktiv behu ki tehiyena le-ish
shtei nashim. No, we have an explicit rule that says חייבי לאוין
chayevei lavin you could be married to. And how do we know?
It's based on a פסוק pasuk from פרשת כי תצא Parshat Ki
Teitzei talking about when a man has two wives, and the wife
he does not like as much has the older son, he has
to choose the older son to be his heir rather than the
younger son. That is, the husband, the father doesn't have the right
to favor his favorite wife's children over the older children from his
less favorite wife. So the פסוק pasuk says כי תהיין לאיש שתי
נשים האחת אהובה והאחת שנואה. ki tehiyena le-ish shtei nashim ha'achat ahuvah
veha'achat snuah. One of his wives is אהובה, ahuvah, beloved, and one
is שנואה, snuah, hated. וכי יש שנואה לפני המקום ואהובה לפני המקום?
Vekhi yesh snuah lifnei Hamakom ve'ahuvah lifnei Hamakom? Does God play favorites?
That is, this is God in the תורה Torah describing the man's
wives. It's not the man himself describing his wives. So does God
know which one is אהובה ahuvah and which one is שנואה? snuah?
אלא אהובה אהובה בנישואיה שנואה שנואה בנישואיה. Ella ahuvah ahuvah benisu'eha snuah
snuah benisu'eha. It must be that one of them, the נישואין, nisuin,
the marriage, is favorable in God's eyes, that is, halachically is a
good idea to marry this woman, and one of the wives actually
is a woman who is not
permitted or favorable to be married to, and nonetheless the נישואין, nisuin,
the marriage, would work. And that's a proof that there must be
women which a man could marry, but nonetheless that he should not
be married to. That is, there must be prohibited relationships which are
תופסי בקידושין. tofsei bakiddushin. Right.
They come רחמנא
כי תהיינה, rachamana ki tihiyena, that you could be married to them.
And לרבי עקיבא דאמר אין קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין, l'Rebbi Akiva d'amar
ein kiddushin tofsim b'chayavei lavin, so what about רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
who thinks that there's no way to marry חייבי לאוין? chayavei lavin?
So כי תהיינה במאי מוקים באלמנה לכהן גדול, ki tihiyena b'mai mokim
b'almana l'Kohen Gadol,
he must be talking about a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the high
priest, marrying an אלמנה, almana, a widow, which is a prohibition not
of לאו, lav, but actually איסור עשה. issur asei. The כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is required to marry a woman who had not been
married before. Therefore the איסור עשה, issur asei, מצוות עשה, mitzvot asei,
because of that is that he could not marry a widow.
It's not a לאו lav because it's framed in the Torah, this
week's פרשה, parsha, כי אם בתולה מעמיו יקח אשה,
ki
im
betula m'amav yikach isha, he has to marry a woman who wasn't
married.
אלמנה וגרושה וחללה זונה את אלה לא יקח.
Almana ugirusha vachalala zonah et
eileh lo yikach.
So it's the way
it's understood based on the דרשות drashot at least, in how you're
saying, it's mentioned explicitly in the פסוק pasuk that says אלמנה, almana,
but the way the חז"ל Chazal understand the פסוקים, psukim, there's no
independent prohibition. It's a לאו הבא מכלל עשה. lav haba m'klal asei.
Exactly. It's a prohibition that's derived from the מצוות עשה mitzvot asei
that he has to marry a בתולה. betula.
So ultimately, we're trying to establish something, you can always say this
is different, that's different, that's something
else.
Well,
there are at least four categories we have to deal with. We
have איסור עשה issur asei category, which basically includes אלמנה לכהן גדול
almana l'Kohen Gadol and very few things else, as far as I
can remember. There are חייבי לאוין, chayavei lavin, which is like a
כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot marrying a גרושה, grusha, or a Jewish man
marrying a ממזר, mamzer, or a Jewish woman marrying a ממזר, mamzer,
and things like that. Then there are the כרת karet ones, of
which there are many, and then there are מיתה בית דין mita
beit din ones, of which there are many. So those four categories
are what we're operating with, and obviously different תנאים Tannaim are lining
up differently about which do have קידושין kiddushin and which don't. It
would be good to make a chart, I'm sorry I didn't make
a chart. I suppose I could make a chart now. Okay, so
we have מיתה בית דין, mita beit din,
כרת, karet, לאו, lav, and עשה. asei. So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
thinks
that there's no קידושין kiddushin for any of these three, but you
could marry someone with איסור עשה. issur asei. רבי שמעון התימני Rebbi
Shimon HaTimni
says that these two there's no קידושין. kiddushin. And רבי יהושע Rebbi
Yehoshua
says only for מיתה בית דין mita beit din there's no קידושין.
kiddushin. That is, besides that within כרת karet and מיתה בית דין
mita beit din there are a few various exceptions about who has
special rules. So for example לאוין, lavin, everyone agrees also יבמה, yevama,
there's no קידושין. kiddushin. That's in the לאוין lavin category. And then
some of these we saw about אשת אח eishet ach has a
special היתר heter in case of the מצוה mitzvah of ייבום, yibum,
and אשת איש eishet ish has a היתר heter after divorce. So
those are exceptions in these categories about other specific circumstances.
נידה. Nida. But נידה nida is a לאו, lav, isn't it? נידה
Nida is כרת.
karet. So נידה nida is also exception here, that's not נידה. nida.
And also
I guess he doesn't care. And then for רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
also not סוטה sotah here is an exception. So those are just
some of what's going on here, and there's much more going on
as well. Okay, so כי תהיינה לאיש שתי נשים. ki tihiyena l'ish
shtei nashim. So לרבי עקיבא דאמר אין קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין, l'Rebbi
Akiva d'amar ein kiddushin tofsim b'chayavei lavin, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says
that you cannot, it is impossible to marry חייבי לאוין. chayavei lavin.
כי תהיינה במאי מוקים באלמנה לכהן גדול. ki tihiyena b'mai mokim b'almana
l'Kohen Gadol. So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva must hold that it's about
אלמנה לכהן גדול, almana l'Kohen Gadol, which is an extended discussion elsewhere.
תיתי דרבי סימאי. Titei d'Rebbi Simai. And it's like רבי סימאי's Rebbi
Simai opinion about what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva holds. Now there's a
מחלוקת אמוראים machloket Amoraim about what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva holds, even
though we don't פסקן pasken by רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. So let's
see. So רבי סימאי Rebbi Simai says: דתניא רבי סימאי אומר מן
הכל היה רבי עקיבא עושה ממזר חוץ מאלמנה לכהן גדול שהרי אמרה
תורה לא יחלל חילולים עושה ואינו עושה ממזרות. D'tanya Rebbi Simai omer
min hakol haya Rebbi Akiva oseh mamzer chutz m'almana l'Kohen Gadol, sheharei
amra Torah lo yichalel, chilulim oseh v'eino oseh mamzerut. So according to
רבי סימאי, Rebbi Simai, all חייבי לאוין chayavei lavin create ממזרות, mamzerus,
except for one exception, which is אלמנה לכהן גדול. almana l'Kohen Gadol.
That is, אלמנה לכהן גדול almana l'Kohen Gadol would
create a חלל.
chalal. So that's this discussion of רבי סימאי, Rebbi Simai, now it's
interesting at least this discussion puts אלמנה לכהן גדול almana l'Kohen Gadol
under a list of חייבי לאוין chayavei lavin and not under עשה.
asei.
Now maybe I've mixed something up. אלמנה לכהן גדול—I'm Almana l'Kohen Gadol
sorry, Dov was right the whole time. I— I'm sorry, דב Dov
was right the whole time, I made a mistake. אלמנה, almanah, a
widowed woman marrying a כהן גדול kohen gadol is a לאו. lav.
What is an איסור עשה issur aseh is a woman who's been
sexually active before but not married marrying the כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
In that she's not an אלמנה, almanah, she's not a גרושה, grushah,
but she's not a בתולה betulah either. And therefore since she's not
a בתולה, betulah, she could not marry the כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
Okay. So רבי סימאי, Rabbi Simai, דתניא d'tanya רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai
אומר omer כל מן היה kol min ha'aya רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
אוסר oser ממזר mamzer חוץ chutz מאלמנה m'almanah לכהן גדול l'kohen gadol
שהרי אמרה תורה sheharei amrah torah לחללו, l'challelo, חילולו chillulo עושה oseh
ואינו עושה ממזרות. v'eino oseh mamzerus. Now the ראשונים rishonim here pick
up on the fact that even though this דרשה drasha is about
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, in fact it should apply as well
to כהן kohen regular marrying a גרושה. grushah. That is, the child
of a כהן kohen marrying a גרושה grushah will not be a
ממזר, mamzer, rather would be only a חלל challal because the תורה
torah has a special category for the children of כהנים kohanim who've
married women who they're not meant to marry, and that's called a
חלל, challal, which is of a higher level, it's one notch down
from being a כהן kohen rather than one notch down from being
a regular ישראל. yisrael. So it's still a higher level of יחוס
yichus than ממזרים. mamzerim.
But wait, what do you mean like practically?
A חלל challal can marry any nice Jewish girl he wants.
But he doesn't serve as a כהן. kohen. So how is it
any better than being ישראל? yisrael?
It's not better than being ישראל, yisrael, it's better than being a
ממזר. mamzer.
That's the difference. I think you say that I, I
mean, I thought someone said better than being ישראל. yisrael.
So most
relationships that a ישראל yisrael has a relationship with someone he's not
allowed to marry, then that child will be a ממזר, mamzer, which
is a drastic reduction in יחוס. yichus. From the level of a
כהן kohen having a relationship with someone he's not allowed to, the
child will be a חלל, challal, so that חלל challal will be
still in many ways comparable to a regular ישראל, yisrael, in which
case it's not so much of an issue.
What if the child of a חלל? challal?
The child of a חלל, challal, male child, will continue to be
a חלל. challal. The question comes up, what about if a חלל
challal marries a ישראלית, yisraelit, regular Jewish woman, then their children, their
girls, will be able to marry a כהן. kohen. That was the
other day. So that is the
granddaughter of a כהן kohen who had an illegal relationship will be
allowed to marry a כהן kohen again.
Does a חלל challal eat תרומה? trumah?
A חלל challal cannot eat תרומה. trumah. חלל challal is not a
כהן. kohen. חלל challal is cut out from the כהנים. kohanim. That's
why it's almost nice. A חלל challal could end up having a
grandson through his daughter who is a כהן kohen again, based on
lining up the marriages the right way. So there is a way
to get out of being a חלל. challal. The way to get
out of being a ממזר, mamzer, there's only one real way which
doesn't work anymore because we don't have slavery. Okay, ואינו עושה v'eino
oseh ממזרות. mamzerus. רבי
שבב Rabbi Shaveiv so disagrees with רבי סימאי. Rabbi Simai. And what
does רבי שבב Rabbi Shaveiv say? דאמר de'amar בא ונצוח על עקיבא
בן יוסף. bo u'nitzvach al Akiva ben Yosef. Let's go get really
upset at רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. What did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
say? שהיה אומר she'haya omer כל שאין לו ביאה בישראל kol she'ein
lo biah b'yisrael הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said
this absurd statement that anyone who you're not allowed to marry, the
child would be a ממזר. mamzer. And therefore what is he saying?
He's saying that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position makes no sense. That
is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position, it doesn't even, it's not fully
spelled out here,
but if you take a look in רש"י, Rashi, פוסל הרבה בישראל
posel harbeh b'yisrael שהיה אומר she'haya omer כל ביאה בישראל kol biah
b'yisrael שאין לו היתר she'ein lo hetter בה הולד ממזר. ba havlad
mamzer.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said every relationship that you're not allowed to
have, the children are going to be ממזרים. mamzerim. That's crazy. Just
sort of almost the סברא sevara argument against רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
That is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has created a situation where there'll
be many, many ממזרים. mamzerim. Many more at least. Just because of
the fact that not everyone keeps הלכה. halakha. And ממזרות mamzerus is
a very difficult thing to get out of.
It's also interesting he doesn't call him רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And
we see also a number of places we saw in the second
פרק perek as well that צוח ריש לקיש ככרוכיא, tzavach resh lakish
k'kruchaya, right? ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
got upset at רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan about הקש
הויה ליציאה. hekkesh havayah l'yetziah. So this very animated בית מדרש. beit
midrash. A lot of yelling going on. Okay. So רבי שבב Rabbi
Shaveiv disagrees with רבי סימאי's Rabbi Simai approach because he doesn't think
that there's this special limitation by אלמנה כהן גדול. almanah kohen gadol.
That is רבי שבב Rabbi Shaveiv thinks that אלמנה לכהן גדול, almanah
l'kohen gadol, the child will also be a ממזר. mamzer. And that's
also a big deal. Now how many כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim are
there at any one time? Not so many. So it's also not
so clear why that of all things is the thing that throws
him over the edge. Okay.
So we say הניחא לרבי שבב hanicha l'Rabbi Shaveiv אי לאפוקי מדרבי
סימאי קאתי i l'afukei mid'Rabbi Simai ka'ati שפיר. shapir. Because if this
דרשה drasha came to undermine רבי סימאי's Rabbi Simai opinion, so that
makes sense, it supports רבי שבב. Rabbi Shaveiv. So then how do
we defend רבי סימאי? Rabbi Simai? Okay. אלא אי תימא דנפשיה קאמר.
ella iteima d'nafshei ka'amar.
Maybe he was saying it according to even חייבי עשה. chayvei aseh.
במאי מוקי לה? bimai moki la? בבעולה לכהן גדול. b'beulah l'kohen gadol.
So and then, so how then what's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva only
exception is בעולה לכהן גדול. beulah l'kohen gadol. This כהן גדול kohen
gadol marries a woman who's had sex before, and therefore that's an
איסור עשה issur aseh because it says מבתולה בעמו יקח אשה. m'betulah
b'amo yikach ishah. And therefore
that's the only exception that doesn't create a ממזר mamzer according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is חייבי עשה. chayvei aseh. So according to
חייבי עשה, chayvei aseh, even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's not
a ממזר. mamzer. But this very limited
case. Other cases not as I've said? No, that was only according
to רבי סימאי. Rabbi Simai. So נידה niddah would not because we
said הכל מודים hakol modim that נידה niddah doesn't and הכל מודים
hakol modim that סוטה sotah doesn't.
So רבי
עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's only two exceptions for ממזרות mamzeirus or three exceptions,
נידה, niddah, סוטה, sotah, and בעולה לכהן גדול. be'ulah l'kohein gadol. Okay,
and isn't it for רבי שבי... Rabbi Shevei... maybe that's a מחלוקת
אחרונים machlokes acharonim or מחלוקת אמוראים. machlokes amoraim. Right. What'd you ask?
So that
child if
בעולה לכהן גדול be'ulah l'kohein gadol
according to רבי שבי'ס Rabbi Shevei's understanding, no, according to everyone, בעולה
לכהן גדול be'ulah l'kohein gadol the child is not a ממזר. mamzer.
Sounds like from this it's not clear. According to at least some
of this it sounds like he would be a חלל, chalal, but
I'm not sure. I think I'm not sure we פסקן pasken that
he's a חלל chalal because it's such a low-level prohibition, איסור עשה.
issur aseh. Or you did ביטול עשה. bitul aseh. ביטול
עשה bitul aseh is a very low-level prohibition. Obviously it's a prohibition.
Okay.
I'm sorry,
so everyone agrees in according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that נידה...
niddah...
yeah, we saw that already. הכל מודים hakol modim that נידה, niddah,
everyone agrees נידה niddah does not make a ממזר. mamzer. Everyone agrees
that סוטה, sotah, that is a woman who's been adulterous, doesn't create
a ממזר. mamzer. Okay. Okay, isn't it with her husband that is,
if the child comes from the adulterer, obviously child is a ממזר.
mamzer. And that becomes the question for then, if the child is
born soon after adulterous relationship, you have to end up relying on
the חזקה chazakah רוב בעילות אחר הבעל rov beilos achar habaal and
things like that, that most of the intimacy between a married couple
is between husband and wife rather than even if there's an adulterous
relationship. And in very few cases then we're able... in most cases
we're able to prevent there being a ממזר mamzer even in case
of adultery based on that. Did you have a question?
If בעולה לכהן גדול be'ulah l'kohein gadol is only an עשה, aseh,
then wouldn't the כהן גדול... kohein gadol... I mean if he has
two wives, marries a wife who was בתולה betulah and he marries
this woman who was בעולה, be'ulah, then what's he doing wrong?
He's still married a woman who is prohibited to marry.
But it's not a prohibition.
It is, but it's an איסור עשה. issur aseh. There's an איסור
עשה. issur aseh. Yeah. איסור עשה. issur aseh. איסור עשה. issur aseh.
That's what you have to say. So that's an issue, you're getting
into some of the נפקא מינה nafka mina kind of questions about
how that works. Okay. מאי שנא משום דהוי ליה עשה שאין שוה
בכל? mai shna mishum de'havei lei aseh she'ein shaveh bakol? But you
can't learn from that, אין שוה לכל. ein shaveh lakol. Now you'll
say a גרושה gerushah for a regular כהן kohein is also a
לאו שאינו שוה בכל, lav she'eino shaveh bakol, but it's at least
שוה shaveh to more people than the כהן גדול. kohein gadol. There's
only maybe two, three כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim at any one time,
right?
At least there was a class.
Right, there's a whole group of people to whom this applies. A
כהן גדול kohein gadol is a singular, singular kind of case, so
you shouldn't try to be learning from that.
ורבנן אדמוקי לה בחייבי לאוין נוקמה בחייבי עשה. v'rabbanan admokei lah b'chayei
lavin nokmah b'chayei aseh. So and the רבנן, rabbanan, that is those
who disagree with רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, held that it applies for
חייבי לאוין chayei lavin but not... so why couldn't they just extend
it to חייבי עשה chayei aseh as well? If you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רבנן דמוקי להאי כי תהיינה בחייבי לאוין, rabbanan d'mokei l'hai
ki tiheyenah b'chayei lavin, that is חייבי לאוין chayei lavin they are
allowed, you are allowed to marry, or it's possible to marry חייבי
לאוין. chayei lavin. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thinks not. So why
don't the רבנן rabbanan agree with רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? In other
words, that it should apply for איסור עשה issur aseh and therefore
even רבנן rabbanan should agree with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that חייבי
לאוין chayei lavin it's impossible to marry. Okay. So why did they
not say like that? Sorry, I lost place. ורבנן אוקמה לה בחייבי
לאוין נוקמה בחייבי עשה הני חייבי עשה במאי נינהו? v'rabbanan ukmah lah
b'chayei lavin nokmah b'chayei aseh hanei chayei aseh b'mai ninhu? So what
חייבי עשה chayei aseh are you talking about? אי שתיהן מצריות שתיהן
שנואות. ei shteihan mitzriyos shteihan senuos.
So then what are you talking about? 'Cause the פסוק pasuk was
talking about a case where a man was married to two wives.
So which חייבי עשה chayei aseh are there that you could be
married to two of? That's the... or one of at once, meaning
what is it talking about? So if both of them are מצריות,
mitzriyos, if he married two Egyptian women, שתיהן שנואות, shteihan senuos, then
they're both bad marriages. Why are we saying he has to
be married to two people?
Because the פסוק pasuk was talking about כי תהיינה לאיש שתי נשים,
ki tiheyenah l'ish shtei nashim, a man who's married to two wives,
one of them he's married to is a permissible marriage and one
is a non-permissible marriage. So the גמרא Gemara is now trying...
are they saying both problematic?
You're trying to say, I don't understand what case you're talking about.
אי שתיהן מצריות שתיהן
שנואות. ei shteihan mitzriyos shteihan senuos. If they're both Egyptian, then they're
both prohibited
marriages. אי אחת מצרית ואחת ישראלית שתי נשים מעם אחד בעינן. ei
achas mitzris v'achas Yisraelis shtei nashim me'am echad bayinan. And then if
you're talking about a case of one was Egyptian and one was
Jewish, then the הלכה halachah about inheritance that that פסוק pasuk is
coming to teach you wouldn't even apply because they have to be
two women who come from the same עם. am. And if it's
a מצרית mitzris who converted, that's not considered to be two women
coming from the same עם, am, מעם אחד שתי נשים מעם אחד
בעינן. me'am echad shtei nashim me'am echad bayinan. אי בעולה לכהן גדול
מכתיב תהיינה לכהן. ei be'ulah l'kohein gadol miksiv tiheyenah l'kohein.
So then why... and if it's only talking about בעולה לכהן גדול,
be'ulah l'kohein gadol, that's רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position,
then that is a כהן גדול kohein gadol is married to two
wives, one was a בעולה be'ulah when he married her and one
was בתולה betulah when he married her, and he has children from
both, he can't favor one over the other. But then it should
say תהיינה לכהן tiheyenah l'kohein or לכהן. l'kohein. rather than כי תהיינה
לאיש. ki tehiyena leish. And therefore Rabbi עקיבא Akiva בעל כרחך שבקה
לקרא דהוי דחיק ומוקי אנפשיה. baal karkhakh shavkah likra dehavi dakhik umuki
anafshei.
So Rabbi עקיבא'ס Akiva's דרשה drasha is understood to be very obviously
difficult to fit into the פסוק. pasuk. That is, the רבנן'ס Rabbanan's
position that it could apply very broadly to many different types of
people married to many different types of women is understandable in that
otherwise the פסוק pasuk would have been more explicit. And therefore Rabbi
עקיבא'ס Akiva's דרשה drasha that the only thing that this הלכה halacha
applies to, a man married to two wives and one of them
he's not allowed to be married to and one he is allowed
to be married to, that only works for כהן kohen marrying a
בעולה, beulah, and that's such a limited case that the תורה Torah
is עיקר חסר מן הספר. ikar chaseir min hasefer.
It should have,
if that's really what it was talking about, it should have been
mentioned explicitly. And that's at least part of why we reject Rabbi
עקיבא'ס Akiva's position.
This says that
Rabbi עקיבא Akiva thinks...
that's
the only case that Rabbi עקיבא Akiva thinks the פסוק pasuk is
talking about?
Right, a כהן kohen married...
a כהן גדול kohen gadol who married two wives, one of them
בתולה betulah and one of them בעולה. beulah.
So the argument is just because this in this one tiny exceptional
case, it doesn't apply, it doesn't mean that it does apply to
every other case that you could easily imagine.
Right, but so the רבנן Rabbanan scootched it back one layer into
חייבי לאוין. chayavei lavin. That is, רבנן Rabbanan understand that קידושין kiddushin
are תופס tofes by חייבי לאוין. chayavei lavin. That is, a כהן
kohen marries a גרושה, grushah, a ישראל Yisrael marries a ממזר, mamzer,
those kinds of cases. ממזר, mamzer, yeah.
So the קידושין kiddushin is תופס. tofes. The קידושין kiddushin works and
the child will be whatever the child should be. An interesting exception,
right? Marrying a ממזר, mamzer, the child would be a ממזר mamzer
even if the marriage worked. That's an exception to the rules of
ממזר. mamzer. So that's also an interesting kind of thing. Anyway, it's
not an exception, it's just kind of the flip side. Once you're
in, you can't escape. Okay, okay. וכל מי שאין לה עליו קידושין.
vechol mi she-ein lah alav kiddushin.
So now the last case in the משנה mishnah was anyone for
whom not only can she not marry this man, she also can't
marry any man. And the two examples are שפחה, shifchah, a slave,
and נכרית, nochrit, a non-Jewish woman. So what is the גמרא Gemara
going to say? So how do we know then the rule there
in the משנה mishnah is that they follow the mother's status? Right?
כל מי שאין לה עליו קידושין ולא על אחרים קידושין הולד כמותה
ואיזה זה זה ולד שפחה ונכרית. kol mi she-ein lah alav kiddushin
velo al acherim kiddushin havlad kemotah ve-eizeh zeh zeh velad shifchah venochrit.
So that is the status of the child follows the mother in
the case where this woman cannot marry this man and also cannot
marry any Jewish man. So why... how do we learn this? וכל
מי שאין לה עליו קידושין. vechol mi she-ein lah alav kiddushin. שפחה
כנענית מנהלן? shifchah kenaanit minalan? How do I know that a שפחה
כנענית, shifchah kenaanit, her children will all be counted as slaves and
not follow the father's status? So אמר רב הונא אמר קרא שבו
לכם פה עם החמור. amar Rav Huna amar kra shevu lachem poh
im hachamor. This is when אברהם Abraham is going to the עקידה
akeidah and he tells אליעזר Eliezer his servant to stay with the
donkey. And therefore עם הדומה לחמור, am hadomeh lachamor, because the nation,
that is, slaves are considered to be similar at least in some
ways to animals in that they don't have קידושין. kiddushin. Now that's
obviously a very harsh דרשה drasha to use to learn such a
basic הלכה, halacha, but we know from a variety of other places
that slaves don't have קידושין. kiddushin. And therefore since they don't have
קידושין, kiddushin, ושפחה לא תפסי בה
קידושין. veshifchah lo tafsei bah kiddushin. So that's just a דרשה drasha
to learn that there's no קידושין kiddushin with slaves.
Wait a second, in other words the comparison between a non-Israelite and
a mule...
Not a non-Israelite, a slave.
A slave, right. עבד כנעני. eved kenaani. עבד כנעני eved kenaani and
a mule. Yes.
Is... I mean a very harsh...
yeah, so it's very harsh.
But is to be understood...
obviously offensive, all that. Let's bracket off those emotions for a moment.
Right.
But is that there's no קידושין. kiddushin.
In other words, but there's something missing in that... like you could
come up with all sorts of implications. Correct.
And in fact one of the similar דרשות drashot that comes up
in the beginning of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, the discussion about whether
or not a non-Jewish corpse is מטמא באהל metameh be-ohel or not.
Because it says אדם כי ימות באהל אתם קרויים אדם ואין
עובדי עבודה זרה קרויים אדם. adam ki yamut be-ohel atem keruyim adam
ve-ein ovdei avodah zarah keruyim adam. So obviously the context there, and
that's a מחלוקת תנאי machloket tannai about whether or not a non-Jewish
corpse is מטמא באהל. metameh be-ohel. But there again it's getting into
almost a very deeply racial distinction between Jews and non-Jews.
So once you have a mindset in which the identity of this
human being in some ways is legally not fully human. Right.
Then you could draw any random implication you wanted in specific contexts.
This applies to whether קידושין kiddushin apply...
does קידושין kiddushin apply?
קידושין kiddushin does not apply to non-Jews. That's what we know. If
you look in the רמב"ם הלכות מלכים פרק ט, Rambam Hilchot Melachim
Perek Tet, the רמב"ם Rambam there talks about the rules of ערוה
ervah for בני נח bnei Noach and obviously אשת איש, eishet ish,
a married woman, is one of the עריות. arayot. So how do
בני נח bnei Noach get married or divorced? For them it's much
more simple. It's the way the... The רמב"ם Rambam describes in פרק
א' Perek Alef in הלכות אישות Hilchot Ishut as well, the way
it was for the Jewish nation before there was מתן תורה, Matan
Torah, that is, people want to live together, they move in together,
if they want to break up the relationship, they break up. It's
very simple. There's no formalized quality. So for קידושין kiddushin and for
גירושין, gerushin, there's a much more formalized, legalized process and that's what
adds that additional halakhic layer which sanctifies and raises the value of
the marriage in the eyes of הלכה, halakha, much more to talk
about that at another time. Okay, so here at least we have
שבו לכם פה עם החמור, Shvu lachem po im hachamor, עם הדומה
לחמור, Am hadomeh lachamor, so non-Jews or slaves at least are compared
to a donkey. אשכחנא דלא תפסי בה קידושין, Ashkachna d'lo tafsei bah
kiddushin, so we know that קידושין kiddushin doesn't work. וולדה כמותה מנלן?
V'valdah kemotah minalan?
So how do we know then that the child of a שפחה
כנענית Shifcha Kenaanit is compared to her, is like her and therefore
will still be a slave? דאמר קרא האישה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה. D'amar
kra ha'ishah v'yeladeha tiyeh l'adoneha.
If an עבד עברי Eved Ivri marries a שפחה כנענית, Shifcha Kenaanit,
which is one of the powers that the slave master has over
him, then the children born to him from the שפחה כנענית Shifcha
Kenaanit remain with the slave master. That is, האישה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה.
Ha'ishah v'yeladeha tiyeh l'adoneha. Therefore the children remain slaves, they're עבד כנעני
Eved Kenaani slaves, and therefore the children follow the mother's status rather
than the father's.
It stays with the master. I don't know you could interpret it
other ways I feel like all what?
What, that
even though they remain slaves, their father could take them with him
or something?
Or that it goes by the father's, right?
Right, but that's what it says in the פסוק, pasuk, right? I
mean, one of the reasons why the אדון Adon has that power
over his עבד עברי Eved Ivri and his שפחה כנענית Shifcha Kenaanit
is that perhaps the most humane way of having more slaves rather
than kidnapping people or capturing people in war is to have the
slaves you already own procreate. So in that respect, it makes a
certain amount of economic sense. We can talk about the ethics of
it as well. But האישה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה, Ha'ishah v'yeladeha tiyeh l'adoneha,
that is if a woman who is a slave has children, those
children are also retained by the same slave master.
Posits it simply as her owner?
Right, exactly.
It's explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. The question is sort of how
do we understand it in a broader frame. Okay, נוכרית מנלן? Nochrit
minalan? How do we know about now this is just a non-Jewish
woman? A non-Jewish woman has a relationship with a Jewish man, the
children will remain non-Jewish. And this is central for the obviously discussions
about
patrilineal descent and all sorts of things. So נוכרית מנלן? Nochrit minalan?
אמר קרא לא תתחתן בם. Amar kra lo titchaten bam. You're not
allowed to marry them. So therefore there's no קידושין kiddushin with non-Jews.
Now תוספות's Tosafot objection here...
No, it's just the opposite, meaning if you wouldn't say לא תתחתן
בם, lo titchaten bam, it would seem to me the marriage would
work.
Okay, so that's going to... that comes up in some of the
ראשונים Rishonim as well. תוספות's Tosafot objection is that that פסוק pasuk
לא תתחתן בם lo titchaten bam is talking specifically about ז' עממין.
Zayin Amamim. That's talking about the Canaanites, specifically the seven Canaanite nations
for whom there's a special מצוה mitzvah to kill them when we
enter the land. There's a special מצוה mitzvah that we're not supposed
to marry them, it's much heightened level of connection of prohibition. And
if you see the רש"י, Rashi, it's a very long רש"י, Rashi,
דדרש טעמא דקרא, d'darash ta'ama d'kra, we'll get to that in a
minute, but there, רש"י Rashi distinguishes between the seven Canaanite nations and
the other non-Jews based on the seven Canaanite nations have a much
more heightened,
deeply entrenched connection to their עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and quotes the
גמרא Gemara from חולין Chullin which becomes a major discussion of the
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah סוגיות sugyas which is talking about אומות שבחוצה
לארץ לאו עובדי עבודה כוכבים הן. Umot shebechutz la'aretz lav ovdei avodah
kochavim hen. Non-Jews who live outside of the Land of Israel are
not considered to be idol worshippers, why? אלא מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם, Ela
minhag avoteihem beyadeihem, that's just called they do what their parents did.
But in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the non-Jews are really פרום. frum.
That's the understanding. That Canaanites are really, really dedicated to עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and that's what's most disturbing about them. And that's why
we had to eradicate them, genocide etc., becomes very problematic in the
in modern lens, but the understanding is that they were very deeply
entrenched in their עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in a way very different
from other nations. That is other nations, even חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
even if they look like they're worshipping idols, eh, מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם,
minhag avoteihem beyadeihem, they're just doing it because that's how they grew
up. But in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they're really... they really take
it seriously. A חרדי chareidi version of the... of the עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, right. So that's an interesting discussion there about sort of...
רש"י Rashi quotes that גמרא Gemara and תוספות Tosafot use that in
a number of places to try to be much more lenient about
relationship with Christians in medieval Europe and obviously extend to that. That's
in the big רש"י Rashi towards the bottom, the דדרש טעמא דקרא
d'darash ta'ama d'kra we'll get to that in a sec. Okay, so
here at least האישה וילדיה... ha'ishah v'yeladeha... okay, נוכרית מנלן? Nochrit minalan?
אמר קרא לא תתחתן בם. Amar kra lo titchaten bam. You're not
allowed to marry them. אשכחנא דלא תפסי בה קידושין, Ashkachna d'lo tafsei
bah kiddushin, וולדה כמותה מנלן? V'valdah kemotah minalan? So now Michael's objection
is for sure, that is, it sounds like לא תתחתן בם lo
titchaten bam either could mean it is impossible to marry them or
there is even though it's possible to marry them, there's a prohibition
to marry them. But at least the גמרא Gemara here understands לא
תפסי בה קידושין, lo tafsei bah kiddushin, it is impossible to marry
non-Jews. And therefore, וולדה כמותה מנלן? v'valdah kemotah minalan? אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai דאמר קרא כי יסיר את בנך מאחרי בניך. d'amar kra ki
yasir et bincha me'acharei banecha. She or he, that is, if you...
Your son marries a non-Jewish woman, then
his non-Jewish father-in-law will lead him astray to worship עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, and he will, he will no longer be in the Jewish
fold. So how do we know בנך הבא מישראלית קרוי בנך? bincha
habah mi-Yisreleit karui bincha? Your son who comes from a Jewish woman
is called your son, ואין בנך הבא מן העובדת כוכבים קרוי בנך.
v’ein bincha habah min ha-ovedet kochavim karui bincha. That is one generation
down because your son has been taken away from the Jewish people.
That is even the next generation, if you have grandchildren born from
this non-Jewish woman, they won't be Jewish anymore. So that's what the
פסוק pasuk is being read to, to say. אלא בנה אמר רבינא
שמע מינה בן בתך הבא מן העובד כוכבים קרוי בנך. Ella bnah,
Amar Ravina: Shma mina ben bitcha habah min ha-oved kochavim karui bincha.
But if you have a, the son of your daughter who was
born to a non-Jewish man, he is called your son. That is
if you have grandchildren from a Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man,
they are called your children, your grandchildren. נימא קסבר רבינא עובד כוכבים
ועבד הבא על הישראלית הולד ממזר. Nema kasvar Ravina oved kochavim v’eved
haba al ha-Yisreleit havlad mamzer. But doesn't Ravina say that the children
born
between either a non-Jewish man or a slave who had a relationship
with a Jewish woman that the child, even though the child is
Jewish, but the child should be a
ממזר? mamzer? נהי דכשר ממזר
לא הוי.
Nehi de-kasher,
mamzer lo havi.
So then you should say that in that case no because it's
כשר. kasher. That is, once you're saying that this relationship,
so how can Ravina disagree with this דרשה? drasha? That is that
when you're saying that it's כשר, kasher, that is, once the relationship
is not totally excluded, once the child is going to be a
Jewish child, so then you should say okay it's not a ממזר
mamzer either. פסול מקרי, Pasul mikrei, but he's still called a פסול.
pasul. That is, if a עבד eved or a ממזר mamzer has
a child with a Jewish woman, the child will not be, not
a ממזר. mamzer. עבד Eved or non-Jew has a child with a
Jewish woman, the child is not a ממזר, mamzer, the child is
פסול לכהונה. pasul l’kehunah. So that's one generation down.
Okay, so I think that's a good place to stop. Just to
note already this what תוספות Tosafot picks up in ההוא משבעה גוים
כתיב, hahu mi-shivah goyim ktiv, שאר אומות מנלן? sha’ar umot minalan? So
then it's from, so the פסוק pasuk is explicit that it's about
seven nations, the seven Canaanite nations. How do we know they apply
to other non-Jewish nations as well? אמר קרא כי יסיר את בנך
לרבות כל המסירים. Amar kra: Ki yasir et bincha l’rabot kol ha-mesirim.
So that includes anyone who would take your child away from the
Jewish nation. That is any non-Jewish woman that it would be equivalent.
הניחא לרבי שמעון דדריש טעמא דקרא. Hanicha l’Rabbi Shimon d’darish ta’ama dikra.
So we should agree that that works for Rabbi Shimon because Rabbi
Shimon is דריש טעמא דקרא. darish ta’ama dikra. That is, he understands
that the context is all about whoever your child marries, the children
are not going to grow up Jewish. So obviously that's כל המסירים,
kol ha-mesirim, anyone who's not a Jewish person who marries your son,
the children are not going to grow up Jewish. אלא לרבנן. Ella
l’rabanan. The רבנן rabanan against Rabbi Shimon do not דריש טעמא דקרא.
darish ta’ama dikra. They don't apply that understanding of the context and
the meaning of the פסוק pasuk to the הלכה halachic conclusion. מאי
טעמא? mai ta’ama? אמר קרא ואחר כן תבוא אליה ובעלתה. Amar kra:
V’achar ken tavo eleiha u-ve’altah. From the פסוק pasuk describing a case
of יפת תואר, yifat to’ar, of a captive woman in war,
אחר תבוא אליה ובעלתה. achar tavo eleiha u-ve’altah. You're only allowed to
marry her and have sex with her after something. מכלל דמעיקרא לא
תפסי בה קידושין. Michlal d’meikara lo tafsi bah kiddushin. That means initially,
at some point initially, it was impossible to have קידושין kiddushin with
her. And therefore, אשכחן דלא תפסי בה קידושין, ashkchan d’lo tafsi bah
kiddushin, ולדה כמותה מנלן? v’ladah k’motah minalan? We know that the קידושין
kiddushin doesn't work. ולדה כמותה מנלן? V’ladah k’motah minalan? אמר קרא תהיינה
לאיש וילדו לו. Amar kra: Tihyenah l’ish v’yaldu lo. So כי תהיינה
לאיש, ki tihyenah l’ish, when a man has children, וילדו לו. v’yaldu
lo. And whoever's children are born to his wives, but it's counted
after their mothers. וילדו לו. V’yaldu lo. The women
raise the children or the women give birth to the children. כהיכא
דקרינן ביה כי תהיינה קרינן ביה וילדו לו. Ke-heicha d’karinan beih ‘ki
tihyenah’ karinan beih ‘v’yaldu lo’. Whoever you are able to marry, those
women are the ones who that your children will be called after
the father's name. But any case where you're not able to marry,
then they would only follow after the mother.